Zhian N. Kamvar, PhD

5026 SE Hawthorne Blvd Portland. OR 97215 H +1 (669) 210-4157 B zkamvar@gmail.com https://zkamvar.netlify.com Twitter: @zkamvar

I am a highly-motivated software engineer of several published packages for population genetics/genomics and epidemiology in the R programming language. As a domain expert in computational biology, software engineer, and a science communicator, I have both the specialist and generalist skillsets needed for efficient communication and collaboration between team members with diverse technical backgrounds. My goal in software development is to ensure that my applications are robust and accessible to researchers regardless of computational skills. Above all, I aim to ensure my software is efficient, consistent, and correct through test-driven developement practices.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Languages: Expert R developer of several widely used R packages (poppr, aweek, incidence) (8 years)

Experienced in creating unique Python 3 modules for population genomic simulation analysis

pipeline (3 years)

Maintained reproducible pipelines in Make and BASH (2 years) for both continuous

integration and HPC frameworks

Implemented recursive and bit-level operations in C to vastly improve speed of R code in

the poppr package

Testing: Practitioner of Test Driven Development, all packages extensively tested (unit, verification,

validation, and regression tests)

Issue Tracking: Highly experienced (8 years) in collaborative development with Git and GitHub; managing

teams and code review

Continuous Highly experienced with Travis (6 years), Appveyor, and CircleCI for automated testing

Integration: on multiple platforms

Bioinformatics: Experience with both Sun Grid Engine (4 years) and SLURM (1 year) HPC frameworks

Developed a Makefile and BASH based variant discovery pipeline for paired-end Illumina

sequencing data

Communication: Highly expereinced in quickly troubleshooting and resolving >200 forum questions in user

forums for the poppr and adegenet packages (\sim 1 day turnaround)

Developed and delivered material for **9 workshops** in **3 disciplines** that reached > **300 people**

Published 19 peer-reviewed publications including 7 first-author publications

SELECTED PROJECTS (ON GITHUB)

R packages: **grunwaldlab/poppr** (maintainer) analysis of populations with mixed reproductive modes

> thibautjombart/adegenet (maintainer) multivariate analysis of population genetics reconhub/incidence (maintainer) aggregation and visualization of disease incidence reconhub/aweek (maintainer) easy conversion betweend date and week formats

Analyses: **zkamvar/clonal-inference-simulations** simulation-based analysis in Python, R, and BASH

> zkamvar/read-processing variant discovery from 55 Sclerotinia sclerotiorum genomes in Make everhartlab/sclerotinia-366 fully automated and reproducible analysis in Docker

TEAMWORK

2018–2019 **Lead Developer**, *R4Epis Project*, Médecins Sans Frontières (Doctors Without Borders).

Collaborated with diverse team of developers and field epidemiologists to create a well-tested series of templates for automated outbreak and survey data analysis.

2018–2020 Coordinator of Software Development, R Epidemics Consortium (RECON).

Worked with software developers, mathematical modellers, and field epidemiologists to design quality standards for software development, validation testing, and analysis of epidemiological data.

EMPLOYMENT

2018-Present Research Softare Engineer, Imperial College London.

Developed well-tested R packages for field epidemiology and modelling

(4 peer-reviewed publications, 1 first-author)

2017–2018 **Postdoctoral Researcher**, *University of Nebraska-Lincoln*.

Population genetics of the white mold pathogen Scleortinia sclerotiorum

(4 peer-reviewed publications, 2 first-author)

2012–2016 **Graduate Research Assistant**, *Oregon State University*, (Dissertation Research).

Development and application of tools for genetic analysis of clonal populations

(9 peer-reviewed publications, 4 first-author)

QUALIFICATIONS

2016 Ph.D. Botany and Plant Pathology, Oregon State University (OSU), Corvallis, OR, USA. Dissertation: Development and Application of Tools for Analysis of Clonal Populations

2007 B.S. Biology, Truman State University (TSU), Kirksville, MO, USA.

SELECTED PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

Kamvar ZN, Amaradasa BS, Jhala R, McCoy S, Steadman JR, Everhart SE. (2017) Population structure and phenotypic variation of Sclerotinia sclerotiorum from dry bean (Phaseolus vulgaris) in the United States. PeerJ 5:e4152 doi: 10.7717/peerj.4152

data/analysis: https://github.com/everhartlab/sclerotinia-366

10.17605/OSF.IO/EJB5Y

Kamvar ZN, Tabima JF, Grünwald NJ. (2014) Poppr: an R package for genetic analysis of populations with clonal, partially clonal, and/or sexual reproduction. PeerJ 2: e281. doi: 10.7717/peerj.281

Personal References

Richard G. FitzJohn (colleague)

Research Software Engineer Department of Infectious Disease Epidemiology Imperial College London r.fitzjohn@imperial.ac.uk

Sydney E. Everhart (former postdoc advisor)

Assistant Professor Department of Plant Pathology University of Nebraska-Lincoln everhart@unl.edu

Annick Lenglet (current collaborator)

Epidemiology Adviser Médecins Sans Frontières (Doctors Without Borders) Amsterdam, Netherlands Annick.Lenglet@amsterdam.msf.org

Thibaut Jombart (line manager)

Senior Lecturer in Genetic Analysis Department of Infectious Disease Epidemiology Imperial College London thibautjombart@gmail.com